K. Aage Strand Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
K. Aage Strand Papers 1875-1999 (bulk 1947-1977)
MSS85428
Strand, K. Aage (Kaj Aage), 1907-2000
15,000 items
16 containers
16 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Astronomer and director of the United States Naval Observatory. Correspondence, speeches and writings, subject files, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating to Strand's research and career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beer, Arthur, 1900-1980--Correspondence.; Bok, Bart J. (Bart Jan), 1906-1983--Correspondence.; Brouwer, Dirk, 1902-1966--Correspondence.; Fowler, William A.--Correspondence.; Fricke, W. (Walter), 1915- --Correspondence.; Giclas, H. L. (Henry L.)--Correspondence.; Hertzsprung, Ejnar, 1873-1967--Correspondence.; Hoag, Arthur Allen, 1921-1999--Correspondence.; Houziaux, L. (Léo)--Correspondence.; Jaschek, Carlos--Correspondence.; Kuiper, Gerard P. (Gerard Peter), 1905-1973--Correspondence.; Oort, Jan Hendrik--Correspondence.; Strand family--Correspondence.; Strand, K. Aage (Kaj Aage), 1907-2000.; Struve, Otto, 1897-1963--Correspondence.; Strömgren, Bengt, 1908-1987--Correspondence.; Upgren, Arthur R.--Correspondence.; Van de Kamp, Peter, 1901- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.); United States Naval Observatory.
Subjects
Astrometry.; Astronomical instruments--Design and construction.; Astronomical photography.; Astronomy.; Double stars.; World War, 1939-1945--Science.
Occupations
Astronomers.
Provenance
The papers of K. Aage Strand, astronomer and director of the U.S. Naval Observatory, were transferred to the Library of Congress from the U.S. Naval Observatory in 2008.
Additional Guides
A detailed container list is available as a PDF document.
Access and Restrictions
The Strand Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Dr. Kaj Aage Strand specialized in positional astronomy, photographic astrometry, and astrometric instrumentation research. His work focused on the determination of stellar parallaxes, proper motions of stars, and use of visual and photographic observation of nearby double stars with an interest in the detection of unseen companion stars in binary systems and extrasolar planets. He is noted for proposing, designing, and supervising the construction of the United States Naval Observatory's pioneering 61-Inch Astrometric Reflector in Flagstaff, Arizona, the first telescope engineered specifically for astrometric purposes. The 61-Inch reflector surpassed refractors in faint object measurement and advanced parallax measurement accuracy from hundredths of an arcsecond to near milliarcseconds. He also designed and supervised the construction of the Strand Automatic Measuring Machine (SAMM) for precision measurement of the plate material being produced with the new astrometric reflector. Strand garnered publicity in 1943 after announcing evidence of a planetary companion in the binary system 61 Cygni AB, which reopened broad public debate on planetary bodies outside of the solar system.
While serving in the United States Army Air Forces during World War II, Strand flew and was chief navigator during B-29 test flights. He was in charge of testing new types of navigation equipment and developing new types of instrumentation for obtaining accurate ballistic data in aerial bombing. He participated in the operational training of special air crews, including the crew of the Enola Gay, first to drop the atomic bomb.
Strand served as International Astronomical Union President of Commissions 24 (Photographic Astrometry) and 26 (Double Stars). He sat on advisory panels for the National Science Foundation, Office of Naval Research, National Research Council, National Bureau of Standards, and Senior Fulbright-Hays Program Committee. He was awarded fellowships from the Danish Rask-Oersted Foundation (1938-1940) and the John Guggenheim Foundation (1946). Samples of Strand's awards include the Distinguished Service Medal, United States Army Air Forces (1946) and the Knight, 1st Class, Danish Royal Order of Dannebrog (1977). A minor planet, 3236 Strand = 1982 BH1 was named in his honor and the 61-Inch Reflector was rededicated and renamed the Kaj Strand Astrometric Telescope in 1997.
Date Event
1907, Feb. 27 Born, Hellerup, Denmark
1926 B.A., University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark
1931 M.Sc., University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark
1931 1933 Geodesist, Royal Geodetic Institute, Copenhagen, Denmark
1933 1938 Assistant to Director Ejnar Hertzsprung, University Observatory, Leiden, Netherlands
1938 Ph.D., University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark
1938 1942 Research associate in astronomy, Swarthmore College, Swarthmore, Pa.
1942 1945 Chief, Navigation Department, Proof Division, Air Force Proving Ground Command, Eglin Field, Fla.
1945 1946 Research astronomer, Swarthmore College, Swarthmore, Pa.
1946 1947 Associate professor of astronomy, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1947 1958 Professor of astronomy; Chairman, Astronomy Department; and director of the Dearborn Observatory, Northwestern University, Evanston, Ill.
1958 1963 Director, Astrometry and Astrophysics Division, U.S. Naval Observatory, Washington D.C.
1963 1977 Scientific director, U.S. Naval Observatory, Washington, D.C.
1977 1979 Part-time consultant, National Aeronautics and Space Administration
1981 1985 Part-time consultant, Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, Mass.
2000, Oct. 31 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Kaj Aage Strand (1907-2000), which span the years 1875 to 1999 with the bulk of material dating 1947-1977, represent Strand's important work in double star photography, astrometry, and astrometric instrumentation design. They offer insight into the collaboration and competition between colleagues on an international level in this field. The papers also document the contribution of one of many Danish immigrants to scientific research in service to the United States military during World War II. The papers are organized largely as received into seven series: Publications; Speech, Lecture and Manuscript File; Correspondence; Subject File; Miscellany; Photographs and Slides; and Books, Notebooks and Journals. The collection material is in English and Danish.
Prominent correspondents include: Arthur Beer, Bart Jan Bok, Dirk Brouwer, William A. Fowler, Walter Fricke, Henry Giclas, Ejnar Hertzsprung, Arthur Allen Hoag, Leo Houziaux, Carlos Jaschek, Gerard Kuiper, Jan H. Oort, Bengt Strömgren, Otto Struve, Arthur Upgren, and Peter Van de Kamp.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in seven series. A detailed container list is available as a PDF document.
Publications, 1930-1981
Speech, Lecture and Manuscript File, 1940-1993
Correspondence, 1875-1997
Subject File, 1942-1996
Miscellany, 1926-1999
Photographs and Slides, 1944-1980
Books, Notebooks, and Journals, 1929-1975
Container List
A detailed container list is available as a PDF document.
- Publications, 1930-1981 (Box RC 1)
  Published works including originals and reprints from American, European, and Russian professional journals.
  Arranged chronologically.
- Speech, Lecture and Manuscript File, 1940-1993 (Box RC 2)
  Speeches, class and conference lectures, draft copies and notes on published works, book reviews, and referee reports written by Strand and about his written works.
  Arranged by type of writing and therein alphabetically.
- Correspondence, 1875-1997 (Box RC 3-RC 8)
  - Special Correspondence, 1937-1994 (Box RC 3-RC 4)
    Copies and originals of letters and memoranda sent and received, mostly between science professionals, academic colleagues, and publishers on matters of professional interest; some is written in Danish.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1935-1984 (Box RC 5-RC 6)
  - Family Correspondence, 1875-1995 (Box RC 7)
    Correspondence between Strand, his mother, sister, and first wife, written in Danish.
  - Other, 1930-1997 (Box RC 8)
    Predominantly post-retirement communications.
    Arranged chronologically, with postcards at the end of the file.
- Subject File, 1942-1996 (Box RC 8-RC 12)
  Correspondence, planning notes, publicity releases, travel and event itineraries, invitation and attendance lists documenting Strand's work with specific organizations, projects, and research. Included are files relating to Strand's contributions to the design, development, and construction oversight of pioneering equipment such as the U.S. Naval Observatory's 61-Inch Astrometric Reflector and the Strand Automatic Measuring Machine (SAMM), and his activities as President of Commissions 24 (Photographic Astrometry) and 26 (Double Stars) with the International Astronomical Union (IAU).
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization, conference, event, or activity.
- Miscellany, 1926-1999 (Box RC 13-RC 14)
  Biographical materials, personal documents, awards, employment records, military records, publications, property documents, master's thesis computations, and photocopies of Strand's scrapbooks consisting primarily of publicity pieces from newspapers and articles published in foreign and domestic press.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or organization to which the documents relate.
- Photographs and Slides, 1944-1980 (Box RC 15)
  Publicity portraits of Strand, construction and dedication of the 61-Inch Astrometric Reflector, samples of early color star and galaxy photography taken with the 61-Inch telescope, conference and event photographs, and personal family photos.
- Books, Notebooks, and Journals, 1929-1975 (Box RC 16)
  Observation journals, student notebook, course lecture notebook, and published books edited by Strand.
  Arranged by type of material.